A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Deputy Director, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid FA592
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Deputy Director, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid
1982-2005
Rockefeller Archive Center
Vaid, Urvashi
Ford Foundation
FA592
3.42 Cubic Feet 9 Hollinger document boxes
Ford Foundation President Susan Berresford established the Peace and Social Justice program in 1996 with the mission of improving government performance and accountability, fostering a thriving independent civil society, and promoting human rights. It was comprised of two global units: Governance and Civil Society, and Human Rights. Social activist, attorney and foundation executive Urvashi Vaid joined the Ford Foundation in 2000 as a Program Officer, and in January 2001, was appointed Deputy Director of Governance and Civil Society. Ms. Vaid launched the Collaborations that Count Initiative in 1998 to support cooperation among state-level organizations working for social and economic justice. She also played a role in the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative and oversaw grants to support gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender rights organizations. Ms. Vaid left the Ford Foundation in 2005 to head the Arcus Foundation. The Office Files of Urvashi Vaid date from 1982 to 2005 and document her work as a program officer and later oversight of the Governance and Civil Society unit. A portion of the records pertain to the Community Organizing Initiative. Other records include her subject files and records from meetings she attended. Also included in this collection are records from the Peace and Social Justice program's work in Russia and Eastern Europe, which date from before Ms. Vaid joined the Foundation. The records illuminate the Foundation's work promoting local governance and democracy in Russia and Eastern Europe following the collapse of the Soviet Union. Also illustrated is a policy discussion on whether and how to evaluate the success of the Foundation grants issued to Eastern Europe.
Organizational History
When Susan Berresford became President of the Foundation in 1996, she established a new program structure consisting of three large thematic programs. Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) was one of these three programs. Its overall mission was to help improve government performance and accountability, foster a thriving independent civil society, and promote human rights. It was comprised of two global units: Governance and Civil Society, and Human Rights. In 2009, Peace and Social Justice became the Democracy, Rights and Justice Program.
The Governance and Civil Society unit continued much of the work of the former Governance and Public Policy unit. Its specific goal, according to the Ford Foundation Annual Report for 1996, was to "stimulate new approaches to designing and implementing public policies, and enhance the role of civic organizations, particularly philanthropies, in promoting democratic values."
Biographical Note
Social activist, attorney and Foundation executive Urvashi Vaid was born in India in 1958 and moved to the United States when she was eight years old. At age eleven she became politically active, and participated in marches protesting the U.S. war in Vietnam. Ms. Vaid attended Vassar College on an academic scholarship and graduated in 1979 with a bachelor's degree in English and Political Science. She then spent three months as a volunteer intern with the Women's Prison Project and worked as a legal secretary and administrative assistant for a law firm in Boston. During the early 1980s, Ms. Vaid helped found the Boston Lesbian/Gay Political Alliance and the Allston-Brighton Greenlight Safehouse Network, an anti-violence neighborhood project. Ms. Vaid attended the Northeastern University School of Law and received a J.D. degree in 1983. From 1983-1986, she worked for the American Civil Liberties Union's National Prisons Project, where she conducted class action lawsuits to improve conditions in American prisons. She then joined the staff of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, serving as Media Director (1986-1989), Executive Director (1989-1992), and Policy Institute Director (1997-2000).
Ms. Vaid joined the Ford Foundation in 2000 as a Program Officer and, in January 2001, was appointed Deputy Director of the Governance and Civil Society unit. A major emphasis of her work was the "Collaborations that Count" initiative, which had been launched in 1998 to support cooperation among state-level organizations working for social and economic justice. Ms. Vaid also played a role in the "State Fiscal Analysis" Initiative, and oversaw grants to support gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender rights organizations. Ms. Vaid left the Ford Foundation in 2005 to head the Arcus Foundation.
Ms. Vaid is author of Virtual Equality: The Mainstreaming of Gay and Lesbian Liberation (Anchor, 1996), and is co-editor, with John D'Emilio and William Turner, of Creating Change: Public Policy, Sexuality and Civil Rights (St. Martin's Press, 2000).
Arrangement
The records are arranged into 4 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Community Organizing Initiative, 1992-2005
Series II. Meetings, 1999-2004
Series III. Subject Files, 1986-2005, bulk 1996-2005
Series IV. Russia and East Europe, 1982-1996
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Urvashi Vaid span from 1982 to 2005 and document her work as a program officer and later oversight of the Governance and Civil Society unit. A portion of the records pertain to the Community Organizing Initiative. Other records include her subject files and records from meetings she attended. Also included in this collection are records from the Peace and Social Justice program's work in Russia and Eastern Europe which date before Ms. Vaid joined the Foundation. The records illuminate the Foundation's work promoting local governance and democracy in Russia and Eastern Europe following the collapse of the Soviet Union. Other documents concern whether and how to evaluate the success of the Foundation grants issued to Eastern Europe.
Additionally, as a Deputy Director for Ford, Ms. Vaid travelled extensively to meetings and conferences related to her work with the Governance and Civil Society unit. She also attended Foundation meetings on policy matters. Ms. Vaid's records for these meetings are available in this collection.
In the summer of 2000, The Ford Foundation established a Fund for Community Organizing to support a collaborative grant-making initiative. The goals of the initiative were to: strengthen the capacity of grassroots community organizations for policy advocacy; assist the development of peer networks among local organizations across issue, race and geographic lines; increase knowledge about the role of community organizing; and broaden the pool of experiences and facilitate the sharing of related information among donors. The Initiative was based on the assumption that community organizing can be a viable strategy for effecting larger social and policy change. The Fund relied on a re-granting strategy by which the Foundation would give grant funds to partner philanthropies who would then issue local grants in pursuance of the goals of the initiative.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Related Materials
FA667 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid, 1992-2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
- Community Organizing Initiative, 1992-2005; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series holds records associated with the Community Organizing Initiative. Several files relate to the Community Organizing Working Group, which brought together the Foundation staff representing the Fund for Community Organizing and the Foundation's re-granting partner philanthropies. Also included are evaluations of the initiative.
  - Applied Research Center -- Background Reports on Anti-Racist Work, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Applied Research Center -- Background Reports on Community Organizing, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Applied Research Center -- C.S. Mott Intermediary Support Program Evaluation, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asian American Women -- Convening Agenda, Report, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Assessing Community Change Evaluation Seminar -- Participants List, Background, 2001 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chicago Community Organizing Capacity Building Initiative -- Site Visit Briefing Book, 2002 October 17-18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Community Organizing Fund Evaluation Seminar -- Project Description, Discussion Materials, 2001 November-2002 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Community Organizing Fund Evaluations -- Progress Reports, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community Organizing Working Group -- Reserve Request Memoranda and Proposals, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Community Organizing Working Group -- Meeting Notes, Reflection Memo, etc., 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Community Organizing Working Group -- Agenda, Minutes, Funding Recommendations, etc., 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Constituency Building Luncheon Discussion -- Notes, 1996 December 6 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation Fund for Community Organizing -- Phase I Report, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation Fund for Community Organizing -- Phase II Report, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Goldfarb Consultancy Report -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Draft Report, 1999 March 3-June 23 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Initiative Statement -- Fund for Community Organizing, 2000 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Peace and Social Justice Speakers Series -- Transcript (Alexi Torres, Sara Gold, Seth Borgos, Chung-Wha Hong, Anthony Thigpen, Marcia Smith), 1998 September 16 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Marcia A. -- Memoranda Re: Community Organizing Intermediaries Meeting, Community Organizing Initiative, etc., 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Meetings, 1999-2004; II
  This series contains files about meetings Ms. Vaid attended as part of her duties at Ford, including the Markets Task Force (2002-2003), the Race and Civil Society Conference (2002), as well as several Freedom of Expression and Democratization of Media Cross-Program Meetings (2003-2004). The files contain minutes, meeting books, correspondence and email, reports, planning documents, and general background information.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Electronic Filing of 990s -- Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, Proposal, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Nonprofit Sector Data Infrastructure Funders Meeting, Ford Foundation -- Agenda, Background, Handouts, 2001 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - United Nations World Conference Against Racism, Racial Intolerance, Xenophobia and Related Intolerance -- Closing Memorandum, 2001 October 16 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Federal Role in Data Infrastructure, Atlanta, Georgia -- Agenda, Meeting Notes, Background, 2001 November 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Markets Task Force -- Workshop Materials, Recommendations, Reports, Planning Memorandum, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Race and Civil Society Conference, Wingspread, Racine, WI -- Meeting Book, Correspondence, Background, 2002 January 11-12 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Midwest Site Visit, St. Paul, MN -- Information Packet, 2002 May 20-22 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Highlander Media Justice Gathering, New Market, TN -- Final Report, Meeting Reports, 2002 August 5-8 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Theory of Change -- Meetings on Revised Theory of Change, Background, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - NGO Rights and Responsibilities, Bandung, Indonesia -- Summary Report, Background, 2003 January 6-8 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Strategic Communications -- Agenda, Background for Talk, 2003 July 24 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Civil Society Grantee Convening, Lake Bluff, IL -- Meeting Book, Notes, 2003 August 3-5 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Civil Society Workshop, Beijing, China -- Report, Handouts, 2003 September 15-19 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Freedom of Expression and Democratization of Media Cross-Program Global Meeting, Queenstown, MD -- Update Memoranda, Agenda, Briefing Info, 2003 November 12-14 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Freedom of Expression and Democratization of Media Cross-Program Meeting, Ford Foundation -- Schedule, Memorandum Re: World Summit, Background, 2004 March 5 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Convening on GLBT Rights and Issues and Religious Traditions in the U.S., Ford Foundation -- Meeting Book, Notes, 2004 April 12-13 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Peace and Social Justice Worldwide Meeting, Rio de Janiero, Brazil -- Notes, Background on Diversity, 2004 November 28-December 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1986-2005, bulk 1996-2005; 1996-2005; III
  The files primarily concern grantees and grant programs, including the Center for Policy Alternatives (1996-2005), the Midwest States Center (1997-2004) and the Social Justice Infrastructure Funders (2002-2005). They contain correspondence with grantees, proposals, notes, and general background information. There also are copies of consultancy reports used as reference for Foundation policy discussions of grant evaluations.
  This series consists of alphabetically arranged subject files.
  - "A Review of UN Reform-Related Projects Supported by the Ford Foundation, 1985-1996" (report by Edward C. Luck), 2001 May 25 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Alliance for Justice Foundation -- Report on Meeting, Reference Background, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - BoardSource -- Grantee Correspondence, Final Grant Report, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Capacity Building Work with Social Justice Organizations" (consultant report by Ann Philbin), 1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Center for Policy Alternatives -- Correspondence Re: Grant Recommendations, Notes, Background, 1996-2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Center for Policy Alternatives -- Correspondence Re: Proposal, Background, Notes, 2001-2003 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Center for Policy Alternatives -- Grant Reports, Background, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Civic Engagement and Bob Putnam Project -- Memoranda Re: Putnam's Paper, Background, Survey Results, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Demos -- Public Sector Report, 2004 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Diversity -- Survey Findings, Susan Berresford Speech, Ford Foundation Affirmative Action Policy Analysis, 1986-2001 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Evaluation Information -- Ford Foundation Archival Materials Re: Evaluation of "Collaborations that Count" Initiative, 2001 August-September (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation Critics -- Articles Critical of the Ford Foundation, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Gay and Lesbian Funding at Ford -- List of Grants, Memorandum Re: Gay and Lesbian Programs, 1998-2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - GLBT Grants and Ford -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation GLBT Programming, 1998-2002 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Governance and Civil Society Program -- Worldwide Collaboration Initiative, Comparative Research, PSJ Grants, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Highlander Research and Educational Center -- Proposal, Correspondence, Background, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "The Influence of Foundation-Funded Research on Public Policy Formation" (consultant report by Deborah Levy and Sarah Smith), 2002 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Lindblom, Lance -- Portfolio Transition -- Discussion Memoranda, Grant Summary with Recommendations, 1997-2001 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "Making Democracy Work" (consultant report by Miles Rapoport), 2001 August (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Message Development/Framing -- Background, Ford Foundation Report, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Midwest States Center -- Grant Reports, Meeting Information, Correspondence Re: Grants, Background (1 of 2), 1997-2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Midwest States Center -- Grant Reports, Meeting Information, Correspondence Re: Grants, Background (2 of 2), 2003-2004 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - National Council of Nonprofit Associations -- Correspondence Re: Funders Briefings, Background, Notes, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force -- Grant Reports, Notes, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - National Organizers Alliance -- Memoranda for Grantee File, Proposal, Background on Pensions for Organizers, 1996-2005 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "New Voices in State Policy: Final Report" (consultant report by J. Phillip Thompson, William McAlister and Esther R. Fuchs), 2000 March 22 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Nonprofit Quarterly -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Potential Sustainability, Proposal for Ford Foundation Support, Background, 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Nonprofits -- Bradley Report -- Article with Comments, U.S. General Accounting Office Report, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "The Peace and Social Justice Program: Goals, Expected Outcomes, and Results" (consultant report by Judith Tendler), 1997 August 4 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "The Philanthropic Response to 9/11" (consultant report by Tom Seessel), 2002 August (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Pushback Network -- Meeting Notes, Background, 2005 April 22-25 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Race, Ethnicity and Access to Democracy" (consultant report by Penda D. Hair), 2001 May (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Social Justice Infrastructure Funders -- Correspondence Re: Meeting, Agenda, Background for Meeting (1 of 4), 2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Social Justice Infrastructure Funders -- Meeting Agenda, Notes, Background (2 of 4), 2003 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Social Justice Infrastructure Funders -- Meeting Summaries, Florida Task Force Reports, Grant Lists, Background, Notes (3 of 4), 2004 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Social Justice Infrastructure Funders -- Meeting Notes, Background (4 of 4), 2005 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Spin Project/Independent Media Institute -- Correspondence Re: Ford Foundation Support, Background, 2002-2004 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Spirit in Action -- Reports, Meeting Notes, Background, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Western States Center -- Proposal, Grant Recommendation, Correspondence Re: Electoral Politics, 1996-2005 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Russia and East Europe, 1982-1996; IV
  This series originated from the Ford Foundation's Governance and Civil Society unit of the Peace and Social Justice program, but pre-dates Ms. Vaid's tenure at Ford. The files primarily concern the Foundation's work in Eastern Europe and Russia following the 1991 collapse of the Soviet Union. The earlier files contain reports about the Foundation's human rights work.
  - "Encouraging Stability, Peace and Justice in the International Order" (report by Joseph S. Nye, Sr., I.M. Destler, I.G. Patel, and Jose Zalaquett), 1987 June (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Evaluation -- Memoranda, Correspondence and Background on Whether and How to Evaluate Russia/East Europe Grants, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "The Ford Foundation and International Security" (report by Catherine McArdle Kelleher and Robert O'Neill), 1992 May (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Funder Lists and Resources Re: Eastern Europe, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "The Future of IREX and Academic Exchanges in the Old Bloc" (report by Edward L. Keenan), 1991 November 15 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Local Governance -- Memoranda Re: Program Opportunities, Background, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "The Overseas Development Council: An Evaluation" (report by Catherine Gwin and Richard Moose), 1982 June (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Overseas Program Review and Meeting of the Board of Trustees, Warsaw, Poland -- Schedule of Events and Related Reading, 1993 September 26-30 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Public Sector Program -- Rural Poverty Program Strategy Papers, Local Government Initiative, Grant Recommendations, Memorandum Re: Closing LDAP USIAP Operations, 1987-1994 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Russia and Eastern Europe: Program Priorities and Office Structure" (report), 1994 June (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Russia and Eastern Europe Program -- Program Description [Czech], 1996 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Russia and Eastern Europe Program -- Program Description [English], 1996 September 4 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Russia and Eastern Europe Program -- Program Description [Polish], 1996 June (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Russia and Eastern Europe Program -- Program Description [Russian], 1996 (Box 9, Folder 14)